Connecticut State Labor Council, AFL-CIO Records 1989.0080
Archives & Special Collections at the Thomas J. Dodd Research Center, University of Connecticut Libraries
Connecticut State Labor Council, AFL-CIO Records
undated, 1909-1991.
1989.0080
Archives & Special Collections at the Thomas J. Dodd Research Center, University of Connecticut Libraries
202.5 Linear feet
In 1957, the Connecticut Federation of Labor and the Connecticut State Industrial Union Council (CSIUC) merged to form the Connecticut State Labor Council, AFL-CIO, generally referred to today as the Connecticut State AFL-CIO. The stated purpose of the new organization was to provide a more effective means of promoting and coordinating the principles and objectives of the AFL-CIO in Connecticut.
AFL-CIO Connecticut State Labor Council.
History
In 1957, the Connecticut Federation of Labor and the Connecticut State Industrial union Council ( CSIUC) merged to form the Connecticut State Labor Council, AFL-CIO, generally referred to today as the Connecticut State AFL-CIO. The stated purpose of the new organization was to provide a more effective means of promoting and coordinating the principles and objectives of the AFL-CIO in Connecticut.
The first joint Connecticut AFL-CIO convention was held in Hartford at Footguard Hall on 13 June 1957. Installed as officers of the Council were Mitchell Sviridoff, President; Joseph Rourke, Secretary-Treasurer and Legislative Agent; Timothy Collins, Vice President; and John Driscoll, Executive Secretary. The constitution drafted by a joint CFL-CSIUC merger committee was unanimously approved by convention delegates.
By 1958, the State Labor Council numbered 644 affiliated unions representing a membership of 155,823 Connecticut wage earners. The Council's net operating capital was $22,462,14. Keith Proudy was added to the Council staff as a full-time Research Director. The following year, a year round Committee on Political Education (COPE) was established for the state of Connecticut. In 1961, Madeline Matchko and Joseph Pennaro joined the Council staff as full-time COPE coordinators under the direction of Ruth Warren Greenberg, Director of Education. By the end of the year, the Council represented over eighty percent of the AFL-CIO affiliated unions in the state of Connecticut.
The year 1962 saw major changes in the state AFL-CIO. Twenty-one new affiliates increased Council membership by 2,117 members. The Council purchased a new office building located at 9 Washington Street, Hamden, CT. Changes in leadership occurred: John Driscoll succeeded Mitchell Sviridoff as Council President; Frances Jones was replaced by Daniel Gallagher as Executive Secretary.
Dwindling cash reserves in 1963 resulted in a reduction of full-time Council staff positions. Despite the economic downturn, the Council was able to increase its membership by adding twenty-five new affiliates. Secretary Joseph Rourke departed after eighteen years of combined AFL/CSLC service to become Deputy Director of the national COPE, and was replaced by Joseph Bober. Keith Proudy also left the Council to become Research Director for the United Rubber Workers. His duties were incorporated into the responsibilities of Education Director Ruth Greenberg.
In 1964, the Council devoted the bulk of its resources to meeting the conservation challenge of presidential candidate, Barry Goldwater. An additional full-time staff position was regained through a grant received by the Council from the Eleanor Roosevelt Foundation. After the election of Lyndon Johnson, the Council turned its attention toward state politics, calling for a constitutional convention to redress the grievances of Connecticut labor. President Driscoll pledged greater involvement by the State AFL-CIO in education and anti-poverty programs.
1966 marked the emergence of the state AFL-CIO COPE organization as a major force in Connecticut politics. Labor outreach was greatly enhanced by the addition of a computer to the committee's voter registration file, giving Council access to thousands of Connecticut voters. In addition, a conference of state central labor councils organized by COPE participated in the formation of a Union Label Services and Trade Council to promote the purchase of union goods and services. The Council's fiscal state improved over previous years', and net operating capital reached a record high of $87,000.
In 1967, the Council celebrated its tenth anniversary. Since the merger of the two labor councils in 1967, ninety percent of all AFL-CIO unions in Connecticut were affiliated with the state SFL-CIO. Despite record high employment and wages in Connecticut, due in part to U.S. involvement in Vietnam, President Driscoll, in his address to the state AFL-CIO biennial convention, called for joint planning by state government and industry leaders for the eventual transition to a peacetime economy.
Efforts toward continuing prosperity, however, were counteracted by a period of internal strife. The suspension of the United Automobile Workers by the AFL-CIO in 1969 resulted in a major setback for the state AFL-CIO. Thirty-four AUW locals with a combined membership of 42,924 withdrew from Connecticut State AFL-CIO. Legislative gains, in comparison to previous years, were modest. By the end of 1969, membership dropped to 141,780.
During the 1970s, the state AFL-CIO participated in several nation-wide labor struggles. These included strikes by the United Farmworkers and the Coalition of Grape Growers. Efforts of the Council to organize public service employees continued with notable success achieved among hospital and convalescent home employees. The Council also aided the United Steel Workers in drives to extend the benefits of collective bargaining to employees of International Silver in Wallingford and Meriden, adding 4,000 new members to the state AFL-CIO. Substantial organizational gains were also made by the Connecticut Federation of Teachers with Council assistance. Despite a steady decline in affiliated locals due to layoffs in civilian and military production plants, overall Council membership rose ten percent.
Unemployment in the mid-1970s, however, continued to hamper the ability of the Council to function effectively. Gains made in organizing public and municipal employees were offset by failures to organize bank and insurance company employees. Efforts to bring about legislative reforms in the area of unemployment compensation and collective bargaining were frustrated by Governor Meskill and by the desertion of key democratic legislators. By the end of 1972, an additional thirteen locals with a combined membership of 1,047 disaffiliated. Three locals went out of existence entirely.
In 1973, Hank Kershner retired as Executive Vice President and was succeeded by Justin Ostro, former President of the Hartford Labor Council. Inflation and unemployment continued to be the Council's primary concern. Despite wage increases in 1973 and 1974, Connecticut workers were unable to keep pace with the rate of inflation. Long sought AFL-CIO sponsored legislation granting binding arbitration to municipal employees was passed in 1975. However, efforts by the Council to expand state unemployment benefits failed.
In 1976, Wallace M. O'Connor succeeded Joseph Bober as Secretary-Treasurer and Legislative Agent. Michael Ferrucci assumed the position of Executive Secretary. Jobs programs and state tax reform were singled out as central issues for the 1976 State AFL-CIO convention. Assistance rendered by the Council to striking locals doubled over the previous year. Executive Vice President Justin Ostro played a leading role in the resolution of work stoppages at the Connecticut Red Cross and Electric Boat.
The Council's twentieth anniversary in 1977 was marked by change and cutbacks in Council services. The state legislative session moved from a biennial to an annual session, prompting the Connecticut State AFL-CIO to adopt an annual convention. Despite intensive lobbying by Council officers and COPE, the Connecticut legislature approved legislation sponsored by the Connecticut Bureau and Industry Association (CBIA) withholding unemployment benefits from workers who quit or were fired from their jobs. The Council was able to make some organizational gains among CTF, ACTWU, ILGWU and hospital workers. The closing of the Dictaphone and Uniroyal companies in 1978, however, reflected the growing impact of foreign goods and competition on Connecticut industry. Faced with a budget deficit of $11,000 in fiscal 1978/1979, Council officers and full-time professional staff voluntarily suspended wage and cost of living increases mandated by the CSLC constitution. Although the demand for Council services continued to grow, further reductions in Council staff left only two full-time officers, two full-time staff members, one part-time editor, one full-time Secretary-treasurer/Legislative Agent, and one part-time President. Moreover, Council officers and full-time professional staff did not have a pension fund or retirement plan.
In 1979, twenty new locals affiliated with the state AFL-CIO, resulting in a net gain of 2,677 members. John Driscoll entered his twenty-second year as President of the state AFL-CIO. Gordon Sawyer was elected Vice President, replacing Justin Ostro, and Dominic Badolato became Executive Secretary. Betty Tianti, formerly head of COPE, became Executive Vice President in 1981, and Carol Colbeth assumed the responsibilities of COPE Director. Substantial gains were made by the Council among AFSCME, International Communications Workers of America, and Service Employees International. Twenty-seven affiliated locals, of which twenty-two locals were unable to meet their per capita assessment, were forced to disaffiliate resulting in a loss of 7,230 members.
In 1981, the State AFL-CIO celebrated its twentieth anniversary in conjunction with the Centennial celebration of the American Labor Movement. Following the annual state labor convention, 10,500 Connecticut AFL-CIO members participated in the Great Solidarity March in Washington, D.C. sponsored by the national AFL-CIO.
Scope and Content
The collection contains a wide variety of materials documenting the activities of organized labor in Connecticut. Included are the files of several Council officers, proceedings, publications, administrative and financial records in addition to publications and information concerning the activities of the AFL-CIO nationally. The majority of the materials date from the 1950s through the 1980s.
Deposits by the CSLC to the Connecticut State Labor Archives have been handled as “addendum” to the original deposit. This information is reflected in the original finding aid to the collection (1989). In the revised version of the finding aid to the collection (1998), addendum materials which continue previously existing series have been integrated as appropriate. New series have been added where necessary. Descriptions of the addenda materials are located in the series description portion of the finding aid.
Arrangement
Series I: Joseph M. Rourke Files ( undated, 1948-1962 )
This series is comprised of materials collected by Rourke while Secretary-Treasurer of the Connecticut Federation of Labor AFL and Secretary-Treasurer of the Connecticut State Labor Council, AFL-CIO.
Subseries A: General Administrative Files ( 1948-1954 )
Subseries B: General Administrative Files ( 1954-1962 )
Materials of interest in these subseries include correspondence with the national AFL headquarters in Washington, D.C., correspondence with local affiliated unions, and correspondence with state legislators and officers. The files are useful in providing an administrative overview of the CFL and the active role this organization played in the merger and creation of the CSLC in 1957. Materials in these subseries also show the extent of activity both the CFL and CSLC organization exerted in fostering the labor movement causes within the state. Material in each subseries is arranged alphabetically by name, title or subject.
Subseries C: Legislative Files ( 1948-1961 )
Contains state and federal materials dealing with Rourke's involvement in legislating various labor bills and causes in the state. Files contain correspondence to numerous state and national senators and representatives. Subject files contain correspondence, pamphlets and other materials. Committee files include minutes, by-laws, and resolutions. When used in conjunction with Series V (Legislative Files) these documents will provide comprehensive coverage of the CFL and CSLC legislative activity. Material in this subseries is arranged alphabetically by name, title or subject.
Subseries D: Political Campaigns ( 1956-1957 )
Contains correspondence for unsolicited political contributions for state congressmen and senators. Material is arranged alphabetically.
Series II: Ruth Warren Greenberg Files ( undated, 1940-1961 )
Subseries A: Teaching Materials ( 1940-1953 )
Contains brochures, teaching syllabi and notes from numerous educational services, schools and workshops. These materials were maintained as reference titles by Greenberg and it arranged alphabetically by subject.
Subseries B: Course Materials ( 1943-1954 )
Includes handwritten notes, examination booklets, syllabi, term papers, as well as brochures from various schools attended by Greenberg. Materials is arranged alphabetically by school and institute.
Subseries C: Education and Information ( 1946-1961 )
Contains administrative subject files including incoming and outgoing correspondence, pamphlets, newsclips and photographs collected by Greenberg while she served as Director of Education and Information for the CFL, and later the CSLC. This material, when used in conjunction with education materials found in the two General Administrative subseries of the Rourke files and the COPE subseries in Series IV, will provide a clear picture of the importance placed by CSLC on education of the worker and activities the organization pursued in this direction. Materials in this subseries are arranged alphabetically by name, title or subject.
Subseries D: Educational Conferences ( 1954-1961 )
Contains correspondence, pamphlets, programs and photographs of conferences and meetings attended and/or organized by Greenberg. The materials is arranged alphabetically by name or subject of conference.
Series III: John J. Driscoll Files ( undated, 1952-1986 ) [see also Series X]
Subseries A: Correspondence ( 1953-1972 )
Contains incoming and outgoing correspondence. Materials is divided into two sections: individuals and CSLC officers, including John N. Bailey, John D. Dempsey, Robert Giaimo, and Norman Zolot. Folders are arranged alphabetically within each section. For Driscoll's correspondence with CT congressmen (1970-1979) see Correspondence subseries in Series IV.
Subseries B: Convention Materials ( 1961-1974 )
Includes correspondence, newsletters and personal papers concerning the 4th - 7th Constitutional conventions as well as the Legislative, Political and Education conventions attended by Driscoll. Material is arranged chronologically by date of convention.
Subseries C: Political and Legislative Files ( 1958-1972 )
Contains administrative subject files documenting activities oaf the CSLC dealing with various state, regional and national issues. Material includes correspondence, pamphlets and reports. For a comprehensive overview of the activities of CSLC, also consult Series IV and subseries A-C in Series I.
Subseries D: Committee on Political Education [COPE] ( 1959-1968 )
Contains correspondence, reports, compiled data and contribution information concerning the involvement of CSLC with the education of the worker. Materials of interest include Republican and Democratic party platforms, information on the 1968 Democratic National Convention, political party leaders, both local and national, and the 1966 election recalls. For additional information concerning the activities of CSLC, its predecessors within the CFL, and the CSIUC, see Series II, subseries C. Also see Series IV, subseries M. Material in this subseries is arranged alphabetically by subject.
Subseries E: Connecticut State Departments ( 1957-1968 )
Contains incoming and outgoing correspondence, committee minutes, reports, and cases pertaining to CSLC and Driscoll interaction with various state departments. Materials of interest include correspondence and cases involving the State Board of Mediation and Arbitration, which includes many state business settlements. Another major portion of this subseries, the Commission on Higher Education, includes correspondence and reports showing the need for Connecticut community colleges, the improvement of scholarship funds available to students, and improvement in teacher certification. Material in this subseries is arranged alphabetically by name of department.
Subseries F: Affiliated Unions ( 1957-1968 )
Contains incoming and outgoing correspondence. Additional information on affiliated unions may be found in Series I, subseries A-B and Series IV, subseries I. Material in this subseries is arranged alphabetically by name of the affiliate.
Subseries G: Councils ( 1959-1968 )
Contains correspondence and newsletters from area labor councils. The material in this subseries is arranged alphabetically by geographical location of the labor council.
Subseries H: AFL-CIO ( 1953-1968 )
Contains correspondence, proposed constitutions, reports and subject files. This subseries is arranged alphabetically by name, subject or title. Related series include Series I, subseries A-B; Series II, subseries C; Series IV, subseries B, M; Series V, subseries M.
Subseries I: Committees and Commissions ( 1961-1984 )
Contains correspondence, reports, by-laws, minutes and subject files of committees and commissions on which Driscoll served. Among these are commissions on education, crime in Connecticut, human rights and governmental relations. This material is arranged alphabetically by committee or commission name.
Subseries J: Conferences and Meetings ( 1966-1968 )
Contains correspondence, reports, by-laws, minutes, press releases, and newsletters providing information on various conferences and meetings attended by Driscoll. Both state and national conferences are represented. The materials is arranged alphabetically by conference name.
Subseries K: Speeches ( 1952-1968 )
Contains reference materials used by Driscoll in preparing speeches for school and public functions. Drafts, as well as final copies, of speeches are included. Material is arranged alphabetically by subject.
Subseries L: Subject Files ( 1956-1972 )
Subseries M: General Administrative Files ( 1977-1986 )
Consists of files relating to the administrative section of the CT AFL-CIO. Included here are correspondence, reports and memoranda. Arranged alphabetically.
Subseries N: Labor History ()
Driscoll's collection of material relating to the history of labor in Connecticut. These sources were used in formulating the educational programs and school kits. For the content of these kits see Series VIII.
Subseries O: Research Reports ( 1974-1982 )
Reports commissioned to facilitate the efficient functioning of the organization.
Series IV: Administrative Records ( undated, 1925-1991 ) [see also Series X]
Subseries A: Correspondence and Subject Files ( 1955-1976 )
Is arranged into several sections. The first section contains the correspondence files of AFL-CIO (National) department heads, U.S. Senators and Representatives from Connecticut; Connecticut elected and appointed government officials; and Connecticut Labor Council Executive Board members, officers and committeemen. Significant figures include John Driscoll, Executive Secretary, CSLC (1957-1962); Mitchell Sviridoff, President, CSLC (1957-1961); and Ruth Greenberg, Director of Education, CSLC (1961-1962). The correspondence from individuals in this subsection is arranged alphabetically by name. The next section is composed of two parts: general correspondence concerning labor affairs and AFL-CIO correspondence documenting CSLC participation as a member of the AFL-CIO. The latter includes correspondence received by CSLC officers from AFL-CIO National headquarters in Washington, D.C., and is arranged in descending order of rank. Included here are new service convention releases, statements by the President, reports and resolutions adopted by the Executive Council, and recommendations by subcommittees and policy committees to the Executive Council. The next grouping consists of general correspondence from AFL-CIO department directors with CSLC Executive Board members, as well as correspondence with their respective CSLC regional, central and local departments. The material is arranged alphabetically by department name. These CSLC/National AFL-CIO files are relatively complete and give a useful perspective on the CSLC role in the American labor movement between 1960 and 1980.
Subseries B: AFL-CIO [National] ( 1960-1975 )
Subseries C: Executive Board ( 1945-1957 )
Consists of CSLC officer correspondence files and Executive Board and Council minutes. Officer correspondence is arranged by title in descending order of rank. Included in the President's files are both internal and external staff correspondence along with President's reports and statements to the Council. The Executive Secretary file contains notices of Executive Board meetings, agendas, and CSLC officers' listings. Director of Education files include internal staff memoranda, letters between central and local education program directors and state education department officials. Research Director files contain correspondence on a variety of issues in the political and legislative fields, directly and indirectly related to the preparation of reports for CSLC officers by the Research Director. The Executive officers' files contain meeting minutes, agendas, committee assignments, memoranda to and from Driscoll, Rourke, Sviridoff, Greenberg, Jones and Collins; along with communication between the Executive Board and state central labor bodies, CSLC officer listings, and confirmations to newly elected members. The pre-AFL-CIO merger correspondence is of particular interest. The Executive Board meeting minutes are organized into four parts: 1—CIO/CSIUC Legislative Committee (1946-1956) which includes correspondence with the Executive CSIUC Council, CT Apprenticeship Council, the state level Democratic party, as well as news releases, meeting minutes and notes, resolutions, telegrams, New England conference reports, and CIO proposals to the CT assembly; 2—CFL-AFL (1945-1955) which includes resolutions, convention preparations, officers reports, communication with affiliated locals, appointments, and general correspondence generated by that body; 3—Merger Committee (1957) which includes meeting minutes concerning the adaptation of convention rules, Council constitution drafts, the election of the new Council officers, the establishment of a CT COPE, and the CFL Merger Committee; and 4—CSLC Executive Board (1957-1956) which includes attendance records and meeting agendas, reports of Executive officers and committees, correspondence with affiliated locals and councils, discussion of new business, and statements and policy resolutions adopted by the Board.
Subseries D: Labor Councils ( 1959-1982 )